<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<juridaljargonSet>

<juridicaljargon jj="felony murder" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A murder committed while the person is also committing a felony.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="dissolution" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The legal end of a marriage, also called a divorce.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="child" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Any person under the age of sixteen (16) years of age.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="community service labor program" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Also called CSLP. A community service program for persons charged with drug offenses. Upon successful completion of the community service sentence, the criminal case is dismissed.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="magistrate" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A person who is not a judge but who is authorized to hear and decide certain types of cases. For example, family support magistrates hear cases involving child support.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="palimony" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> term has meaning similar to `alimony' except that award, settlement or agreement arises out of non-marital relationship of parties (i.e., non-marital partners)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="court services officer" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A person who assists the judge and oversees cases as they go through the court.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="non-financial bonds" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description>     a) Non-surety bond where the defendant's signature alone guarantees the amount of bond and the defendant is not required to post any property or retain the services of a professional bail bondsperson as collateral.     b) Promise to appear.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="neglected minor" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A child or youth who has (a) been abandoned, (b) is being denied proper attention, (c) is being permitted to live under conditions injurious to his/her well being, or (d) has been abused.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="lis pendens" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A pending lawsuit. Jurisdiction or control that courts have over property in a case waiting for final disposition. A notice of lis pendens is filed on the land records.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="adjudication" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A decision or sentence imposed by a judge.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="protective order" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A criminal court order issued by a judge to protect a family or household member.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="charge" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Formal accusation of a crime.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="cross- examination" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> questioning by a party or his attorney of an adverse party or a witness called by an adverse party</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="drug court" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A Special Session of the Superior Court that is responsible for hearing cases involving charges of drug offenses.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="case" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A lawsuit or action in a court.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="parcel" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a tract or a plot of land</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="appeal bond" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Money paid to the court while taking an appeal to cover costs and damages to the other party, if the appeal is not successful.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="liability" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an obligation to do, to eventually do, or to refrain from doing something; money owed; or according to law one's responsibility for his/her conduct; or one's responsibility for causing an injury</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="redact" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> to edit, revise</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="special verdict" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a special finding of the facts of a case by a jury leaving to the court the application of the law to the facts thus found</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="bond review" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A hearing for a judge to decide if the defendant’s bond amount needs to be changed.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="non-suit" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Vacating a case by the court, usually for failure to prosecute.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="venue" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description>1. Geographical place where some legal matter occurs or may be determined. 2. The geographical area within which a court has jurisdiction. It relates only to a place or territory within which either party may require a case to be tried. A defect in venue may be waived by the parties.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="verdict" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the determination of a jury on the facts</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="eviction, warrant of" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Legal mandate authorizing an enforcement officer to remove persons and their personal property from their premises.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="indemnity" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Security against loss or damages, exemption from penalty or liability, amount paid as compensation under an indemnity agreement.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="chip smith charge" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> is an instruction to deadlocked jurors in civil and criminal cases, urging those jurors who disagree with the majority vote to reexamine the majority views in an effort to reach a unanimous verdict.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="probate/probate court" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A court with limited authority to hear certain kinds of cases, such as adoption, guardianship, mental health commitments. Not a part of the Superior Court system.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="senior judge" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A judge who reaches the age of 65, or who meets certain other requirements and chooses senior status. Senior judges hear cases on a part time basis until they reach the mandatory retirement age of 70.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="injunction" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a court order for a party to stop doing or to start doing a specific act</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="actual place of business" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Any location that the defendant, through regular solicitation or advertisement, has held out as its place of business (sec. 308.6 CPLR).</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="family relations counselor" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A person who mediates disagreements and negotiates agreements in custody, visitation and divorce cases. At the request of the judge, a family relations counselor may evaluate a family situation by interviewing each parent and the children in the family. The family relations counselor then writes a report for the judge, making recommendations about custody and visitation. Works in the Family Services Office.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="enjoin" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> to require a person, by writ of injunction from a court of equity, to perform or to abstain or desist from some act</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="stpulation of settlement" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> A formal agreement between litigants and/or their attorneys resolving their dispute.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pretrial hearing" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Conference with attorneys to determine scope of possible trial with view toward resolving issues through agreement.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="short calendar" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A list of cases in which hearing by the judge or magistrate is requested or required.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="surety" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> One who is legally liable for the debt, default, or failure to carry out a duty of another.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="brief" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a written or printed document prepared by the lawyers on each side of a dispute and submitted to the court in support of their arguments - a brief includes the points of law which the lawyer wished to establish, the arguments the lawyer uses, and the legal authorities on which the lawyer rests his/her conclusions.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="interrogatories" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> written questions propounded by one party and served on an adversary, who must provide written answers thereto under oath</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="bail commissioner" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A state-appointed person who may set the amount of bond for persons detained at a police station prior to arraignment in court, and who recommends to the court the amount of bond that should be set for the defendant on each criminal case.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="reply" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a plaintiff's response to a defendant's answer when the answer contains a counterclaim</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="appeal" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a proceeding to have a case examined by an appropriate higher court to see if a lower court's decision was made correctly according to law</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jury" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a prescribed number of persons selected according to law and sworn to make findings of fact</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="bifurcated trial" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a case in which the trial of the liability issue in a personal injury or wrongful death case is heard separate from and prior to trial of the damages in question</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jury instructions" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> directions given by the judge to the jury</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="consolidated action" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> two or more actions involving a common question of law or fact may be consolidated by the court; the actions then are merged, becoming one action with one title, and they result in one verdict and one judgment</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="deposition" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> sworn testimony of a witness</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="minor" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A person under age 18, the age of legal majority.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="separation" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> in matrimonial law, a cessation of cohabitation of husband and wife by mutual agreement, or in the case of "judicial separation," under the decree of a court</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="common law" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the body of law which originated in England and upon which present day U.S. law is based</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="forum" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> A judicial tribunal or a place of jurisdiction. A meeting for discussion.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="petitioner" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> In a special proceeding, one who commences a formal written application, requesting some action or relief, addressed to a court for determination. Also known as a plaintiff in a civil action</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="trial" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the formal examination of a legal controversy in court so as to determine the issue</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="action" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a civil judicial proceeding whereby one party prosecutes another for a wrong done or for protection of a right or prevention of a wrong; requires service of process on adversary party or potentially adversary party</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="aka" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> "Also known as". Used to list aliases or another name, or another spelling of a name used by a person.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="affidavit of service" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an affidavit intended to certify the service of a writ, notice, or other document</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="plea" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> An accused persons answer to a criminal charge. For example</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="petit jury" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the ordinary jury for the trial of a civil case (so called to distinguish it from the grand jury)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="certificate of readiness" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a document attesting that the parties in a lawsuit are ready to go to trial</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="day incarceration center" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Also called DIC. A community based program that provides monitoring, supervision and services to people who would otherwise be incarcerated. Day Incarceration Center clients are supervised during the daytime hours, seven days per week.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="conviction" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> To be found guilty of committing a crime.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="state referee" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A retired judge who presides over cases referred by the court with agreement of counsel for both parties. Has full powers of an active trial judge.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="sanction" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a penalty or punishment provided as a means of enforcing obedience to a law, rule or code; also, an authorization</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="directed verdict" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an instruction by the judge to the jury to return a specific verdict</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="no contact order" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A court order that prohibits contact by a defendant with a victim; can be ordered by a judge, a bail commissioner, a probation officer or a parole officer.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="fee" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a fixed charge for service rendered on behalf of court</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="investigatory grand jury" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A judge, constitutional state referee or any three judges of the Superior Court, appointed by the Chief Court Administrator to conduct an investigation into the commission of a crime or crimes.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="liber" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a book used for keeping a record of specific documents or events having legal effect</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pro se divorce" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Do it yourself divorce - (en epañol).</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in re" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> In the matter of; concerning.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="certiorari" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a proceeding in the state Supreme Court under Art. 78 of the CPLR to review the decisions or actions of a public official or body, as in a tax certiorari matter, a review of the tax assessed challenge an exception taken to a juror before he/she is sworn challenge for a challenge based on a legally specified reason</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="garnish" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> to attach a portion of the wages or other property of a debtor to secure repayment of the debt</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="defendant" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the party being sued or the party accused of committing the offense charged</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="note of issue" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a document filed with the court placing a cause on the trial calendar</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="award" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> A decision of an Arbitrator.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="trial de novo" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> A new trial (see</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="capias mittimus" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A civil arrest warrant used to get a person physically into court to respond to a specific case or claim.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="counterclaim" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> 1. In civil actions, a claim brought by a defendant against the plaintiff for an unlimited amount of money. 2. In small claims/commercial claims, a claim brought by a defendant against the plaintiff for an amount not to exceed the maximum monetary jurisdiction allowed in the small claims/commercial claims court.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="challenge" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Rejecting a potential juror.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="wage execution" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The process of deducting money from wages to pay a judgment. Also called a garnishment or attachment.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="purge" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> To atone for an offense, to submit to a court's mandate (i.e., to purge oneself of contempt of court)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="indorsed complaint" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> A statement of the nature and substance of the cause of action, for money only, which indicates the amount of the claim. It may be set forth upon the summons or attached to it. INFANT An individual who has not attained the age of eighteen (18).</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="return date" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The date on which the 90-day waiting period for a divorce begins. Also, the date that starts the countdown for things taking place in a case, including the deadlines for filing certain papers, including the date by which the defendant should file an appearance. Nothing happens in court on the return date and no one needs to go to court on the return date. The return date is always a Tuesday in civil and family cases. In summary process (eviction) cases, the return date is any week day, Monday through Saturday, except a holiday, usually 7 to 10 days from the date the clerk signs the summons if the summons is signed by the clerk.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="claim" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> In civil cases, the statement of relief desired.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="juvenile probation" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Placement of an adjudicated delinquent under the supervision of a juvenile probation officer.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="regional family trial docket" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A specialized court designed to hear complicated family cases. One judge hears the case from start to finish. Located in Middletown.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="prosecute" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> To carry on a case or judicial proceeding. To proceed against a person criminally.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="process" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a legal means, such as a summons, used to subject a defendant in a lawsuit to the jurisdiction of the court; broadly, refers to all writs issued in the course of a legal proceeding</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="small claims" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Civil actions to recover damages, or money, up to $5000.The rules of evidence are relaxed and people often represent themselves instead of hiring an attorney.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ga - geographical area" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Geographical Area. The court location where motor vehicle and most criminal cases are heard. There are 22 Geographical Areas in Connecticut.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="allege" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> To assert a fact in a pleading.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="probation absconder" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A person under probation supervision whose location is unknown, in violation of the conditions of their probation.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="restitution" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Money ordered to be paid by the defendant to the victim to reimburse the victim for the costs of the crime. Generally making good, or giving the equivalent for any loss, damage or injury caused by a persons actions. Often a condition of probation.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pro se" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> for oneself; in one's own behalf; in person; a pro se party is one who, without representation, acts as his/her own attorney</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="office of adult probation" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A division within the Judicial Branch. The primary responsibilities of the Office of Adult Probation are to supervise persons placed on probation, to conduct investigations for the court to provide background information on convicted offenders and to conduct eligibility investigations for special programs.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="practice book" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Contains the rules of court and forms which must be followed in all Connecticut court cases. Available in all courthouse law libraries.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="attachment" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> The taking of property into legal custody by an enforcement officer (see specialty section</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="answer" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a paper submitted by a defendant in which he/she responds to and/or denies the allegations of the plaintiff</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="trial assignment part (tap)" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> that part of the court which assigns cases for trial (NYS)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="subsequent proceedings" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Any proceeding or action taken with respect to a specific case after it has been filed with the court.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="public defender" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> An attorney appointed and paid by the state who defends a person in a criminal case after the court finds that the person is indigent--financially unable to hire a private attorney.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="no contest" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A plea in a criminal case that allows the defendant to be convicted without admitting guilt for the crime charged. Also called nolo contendre. Although a finding of guilty is entered on the criminal court record, the defendant can deny the charges in a civil action based on the same acts.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="arrearages" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Money for alimony and/or child support, which is overdue and unpaid.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="perjury" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the act of lying or stating falsely under oath</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="alford doctrine" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A plea in a criminal case in which the defendant does not admit guilt, but agrees that the state has enough evidence against him or her to get a conviction. Allows the defendant to enter into a plea bargain with the state. If the judge accepts the Alford Plea, a guilty finding is made on the record.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="incompetency" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> lack of legal qualification or fitness (physical, intellectual or moral fitness) to discharge a legally required duty or to handle one's own affairs; also relates to matters not admissible in evidence</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="sentencing" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> When a criminal defendant is brought before a judge after conviction for ordering the terms of the punishment.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="assignment list" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A printed list of cases to be presented to the court for hearing.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="docket number" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A unique number the court clerk assigns to a case. It must be used on all future papers filed in the court case. Each docket number starts with two letters that tell the type of case. CI = criminal infraction; CR = criminal case; CV = civil case; FA = family case; MI = motor vehicle infraction; MV= motor vehicle case; SC = small claims.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="crossclaim" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> claim litigated by co-defendants or co-plaintiffs against each other and not against a party on the opposite side of the litigation</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="memorandum opinion" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> memorandum in writing, which is a very brief statement of the reasons for a decision, without detailed explanation</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="fine" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a sum imposed as punishment for an offense</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="attestation" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the act of witnessing an instrument in writing at the request of the party making the same, and subscribing it as a witness</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="writ" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an order issuing from a court of justice and requiring the performance of a specified act, or giving authority and commission to have it done</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="order" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an oral or written direction of a court or judge</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="foreclosure" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a legal proceeding that bars or extinguishes right</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="misdemeanor" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A crime that carries a maximum penalty of one year and/or a $2,000 fine.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="alternative detention program" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Programs operated by service providers under the Office of Alternative Sanctions used to detain juveniles instead of in a Juvenile Detention Center.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="exemplification" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> An official transcript of a document from public records, made in a form to be used as evidence and authenticated or certified as a true copy, (e.g. exemplification of a judgment).</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="interpreter" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a person sworn at a judicial proceeding to translate oral or written language</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="court trial" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Trial by a judge, rather than by a jury.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="special sessions of the superior court" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A program of the Judicial Branch where cases of a single type are heard by the same judge through the entire case. For example</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="dispose" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the act of terminating a judicial proceeding</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="tort" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an injury or wrong committed, either with or without force, and either intentionally or negligently, to the person or property of another</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="juvenile detention center" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A secure facility for juveniles operated by the Division of Juvenile Detention Services of the Connecticut Judicial Branch, open 24 hours a day, 7 days a week.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="mittimus judgment" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Also called a Mitt. The formal document prepared by the court clerk to present a convicted defendant in a criminal case to the Department of Correction for incarceration.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="petition" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a formal written request to a court, which initiates a special proceeding</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="wage withholding" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A court order to deduct child support or alimony payments from someone’s wages. All child support court orders must include an income withholding order unless both parents ask the judge not to.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="community services coordinator" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The person who refers a defendant to community service work and supervises the defendant’s completion of that work.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="assistant attorney general" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> An attorney who represents a state agency in civil cases.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="bond forfeiture (calling the bond)" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> If the defendant fails to appear in court as scheduled, the judge may order the bond forfeited (paid to the state) and the defendant rearrested.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="venire" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> technically, a writ summoning persons to court to act as jurors; popularly used as meaning the body of names thus summoned</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="juvenile court" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Also called Superior Court for Juvenile Matters. A special division of the Superior Court designated to hear all cases concerning uncared for, dependent children and youth and delinquents. All juvenile court proceedings and case records are confidential and are not public information.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="alternative dispute resolution" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Also called ADR. Any method used to resolve disputes other than traditional trial proceedings. For example, mediation. ADR programs speed up the disposition of civil cases.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="regional child protection docket" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A specialized court designed to hear complicated child protection cases. One judge hears the case from start to finish. Located in Middletown.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="declaratory judgment" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> one fixing rights of parties without ordering anything to be done</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="paternity" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Legal fatherhood.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ne exeat" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A legal paper requesting that a person be required to remain within the jurisdiction of the court (either through incarceration or posting of a bond.)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="undertaking" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Deposit of a sum of money or filing of a bond in court.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="preclude" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> To prevent or stop</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="adjournment" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a temporary postponement of the proceedings of a case until a specified future time</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="attorney of record" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> attorney whose name appears in the permanent records or files of a case</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="affiant" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> one who swears to an affidavit; deponent</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="lockout" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Illegally forcing a tenant out of rented property, usually by changing the locks on the doors.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="bond" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Also called bail. Money or property given to the court for the temporary release of a defendant, to ensure that the defendant will return to court. There are two kinds of bonds</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="consolidate" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> A joining of two or more actions to be tried together.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="rule to show cause" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Summons compelling a person to appear in court on a specific date to answer to a request that certain orders be modified or vacated.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="de novo" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> From the beginning, a new trial.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="cross-examination" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Questioning by a party or the attorney of an adverse party or a witness.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="sentence review" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A defendant’s written application to a three judge panel to review the sentence. Must be filed within 30 days after being sentenced with the court clerk. A review decision can increase or decrease the sentence.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="joint trial" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> two or more actions involving a common question of law or fact may be joined by court order for trial - the actions are not merged but remain separate and distinct and may result in one or more verdicts and judgments</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="statute of limitations" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a statute that declares that no actions of a specified kind be commenced after a specified period of time after the cause of action arose</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="case flow coordinator" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A person who keeps track of your case and supervises the scheduling of hearings and trials.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="witness" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> one who testifies to what he/she has seen, heard, or otherwise observed</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="calendar call" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the calling of matters requiring parties, or their attorneys, to appear and be heard, usually done at the beginning of each court day</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="decree" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a decision or order of the court - a final decree is one which fully and finally disposes of the litigation; an interlocutory decree is a provisional or preliminary decree which is not final</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="amicus curiae brief" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A Latin term meaning “friend of the court.” An Amicus Curiae brief is filed by someone who is not a party to a case but has an interest in its outcome. A person who wants to file an amicus curiae brief usually has to get the court’s permission to do so.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="acknowledgment" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the act of going before a qualified officer (e.g., Clerk) and declaring the validity of the document. The officer certifies same, whose certification is known as the acknowledgment</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="notarize" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> To formally complete a document by acknowledgement or oath.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="res" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Subject matter</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="dismissal" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> termination of a proceeding for a procedurally prescribed reason</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="adult probation" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A legal status, applied to people 16 years of age and older, who have been convicted of a crime and placed under the supervision of a probation officer for a period of time set by the court.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="promise to appear" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A type of non-financial bond where the defendant agrees to return to court without giving cash or property.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="plea bargain" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The agreement a defendant makes with the prosecutor to avoid a trial. Usually involves pleading guilty to lesser charges in exchange for a lighter sentence.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="time served" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A sentence of incarceration equal to the amount of time a defendant has already spent in state custody waiting for disposition of the case.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="alternative sanctions" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Criminal punishment that is less restrictive than incarceration.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="laches" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the failure to diligently assert a right, which results in a refusal to allow relief</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="disposition" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the result of a judicial proceeding by withdrawal, settlement, order, judgment or sentence</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="material witness" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> person whose testimony on some issue has been judicially determined as relevant and substantial</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="direct examination" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the first interrogation of a witness by the party on whose behalf the witness is called</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="replevin" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an action brought for the owner of items to recover possession of those items when those items were wrongfully taken or are being wrongfully kept</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="motion" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an oral or written request to the court made by a party for a ruling or order</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="caption" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> in a pleading, deposition or other paper connected with a case in court, it is the heading or introductory clause which shows the names of the parties, name of the court, number of the case on the docket or calendar, etc.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="hearsay" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a type of testimony given by a witness who relates not what he/she knows personally, but what others have told the witness, or what the witness has heard said by others; may be admissible or inadmissible in court depending upon rules of evidence</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="continuance date" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Date on which the case will next be heard in court.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="hearing" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a preliminary examination where evidence is taken for the purpose of determining an issue of fact and reaching a decision on the basis of that evidence</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="sequester" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> to separate, set apart, hold aside for safekeeping or awaiting some determination; jurors are sequestered when not permitted to return home until the case is closed</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="probation" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> When a convicted offender receives a suspended term of incarceration and is then supervised by a probation officer for a period of time set by a judge.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="charge to jury" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> in trial practice, an address delivered by the court to the jury at the close of the case instructing the jury as to what principles of law they are to apply in reaching a decision</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="arbitration" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the submission voluntarily or involuntarily of a disputed matter to selected persons and the substitution of their award or decision for the judgment of a court or its confirmation by the court as a judgment of the court</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="parenting education program" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A mandatory program for persons involved in a divorce with children or a custody or visitation case. Must be attended within 60 days of the return date on the summons.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="service" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the exhibition or delivery of a writ, notice, etc., officially notifying a person of some action or proceeding in which that person is concerned</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="subpoena duces tecum" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a subpoena requiring a person to produce specified documents or records in a trial</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="alternative incarceration center" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Also called AIC. A community based program that provides monitoring, supervision and services to people who would otherwise be incarcerated.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="legal separation" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A court order describing the conditions under which two married people will live separately.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="long form order" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an order prepared by counsel for signature of the court (usually based on a memorandum decision)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="case conference" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A meeting scheduled by the court to review the case.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="part" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a court room where specified business of a court is to be conducted by a judicial officer</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="nolle" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Short for nollo prosequi, which means "no prosecution". A disposition of a criminal or motor vehicle case where the prosecutor agrees to drop the case against the defendant but keeps the right to reopen the case and prosecute at any time during the next thirteen months. The nolle is entered on the court record and the defendant is released from custody. If the defendant stays out of trouble during the thirteen months, the case is removed from the official court records.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="easement" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> right held by one person to use the land of another for a special purpose</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in camera" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> in the judge's chamber out of the presence of the jury and the public</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="youth" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Any person sixteen (16) to eighteen (18) years of age.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="chattels" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> All property except real property; personal property. For example</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="subpoena (judicial)" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an order issued by the court to a person to attend court and give testimony</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="family support magistrate" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A person who decides cases involving child support and paternity. Can also enforce court orders involving paternity, child support and alimony.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="oath" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a swearing to the truth of a statement which, if made by one who knows it to be false, may subject one to a prosecution for perjury or other legal proceedings</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="exhibit" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a paper, document or other article produced and exhibited to a court during a trial or hearing and, on being accepted, is marked for identification or admitted in evidence</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="continuance" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The adjournment or postponement of a court case to another day.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="recuse" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> To disqualify oneself as a judge</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="youthful offender" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The legal status of persons who have been arrested for a crime committed when they were between the ages of 16 and 18 and who meet other requirements. All 16- and 17- year-old defendants are treated as youthful offenders, except those who have been charged with certain felonies, have already been convicted of a felony on the adult docket, or have been adjudicated as a serious juvenile offender. For defendants treated as Youthful Offenders, the information and proceedings are confidential and do not become a part of the person’s criminal record.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="argument" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a reason given in proof or rebuttal</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="judgment roll" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a record of the judgment with the supporting papers</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="memorandum decision" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a written opinion or decision of a court on a litigated question, giving the court's conclusion on factual and legal issues (this may constitute the order of the court if so stated)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="sentences" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The penalty imposed by a judge after the defendant is convicted of a crime. Sentences can be</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="judgment file" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A permanent court record of the court’s final disposition of the case.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="commissioner of jurors" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a person in charge of summoning citizens for jury duty</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="electronic monitoring" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> An electronic system that provides the Probation Officer or Bail Commissioner a report about whether the offender has left home during the time when the offender was required to remain at his or her home.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="voir dire" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a questioning of prospective jurors by the attorneys, and, on application of any party, by the judge, to see if any of them should be disqualified or removed by challenge or examination</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="infant's compromise" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a civil proceeding or motion for obtaining court approval of the settlement of an infant's claim</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="dismissal with prejudice" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Action dismissed on the merits which prevents renewal of the same claim or cause of action.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="small claims assessment review (scar)" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> filing by any person aggrieved by an assessment of a one, two or three family, owner occupied residential structure used for residential purposes (including condominiums) (NYS)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="impaneling" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the process by which jurors are selected and sworn to their task</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="finding" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the court's or jury's decision on issues of fact</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex parte" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a proceeding, order, motion, application, request, submission etc., made by or granted for the benefit of one party only; done for, in behalf of, or on application of one party only</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="subpoena" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Legal process which commands a witness to appear and testify.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="foreman" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> An elected member of a jury who delivers the verdict to the court.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="first paper" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Paper instituting the action (e.g., Summons, Motion, Infants's Compromise).</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="summons" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> A form used to commence a civil action and acquire jurisdiction over a party</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="affirmation" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> A solemn and formal declaration under penalties of perjury that a statement is true, without an oath.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="clerk's minutes" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> notes, which are taken by a clerk, of events that occurred in court</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="support enforcement officer" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A person who supervises child support payments and brings parents to court to enforce child support orders. May also file legal papers to modify or change child support orders.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="emancipation" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The release of a youth from the legal authority and control of the youth's parents and the corresponding release of the youth’s parents from their obligations to the youth.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="transcript" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the official record of proceedings in a trial or hearing</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="special proceedings" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> general term for remedies or proceedings which are not ordinary actions, e.g., condemnation</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="statute" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A law enacted by a legislative body.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="annul" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> to make void, as to dissolve the bonds of marriage</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="family with service needs" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Also called FWSN. A family that includes a child, who (a) runs away without just cause, (b) is beyond the control of his/her parents/guardian, (c) has engaged in indecent or immoral conduct, and/or (d) is a truant or continuously defiant of school rules and regulations.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="mediation" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A dispute resolution process in which an impartial third party assists the parties to voluntarily reach a mutually acceptable settlement.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="consanguinity" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Related by blood.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="filing" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Giving the court clerk legal papers which become part of the case file.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="affirmed" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Upheld, agreed with (e.g.,The Appellate Court affirmed the judgment of the City Court).</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="bondsman" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A surety; one who has put up cash or property as collateral before a defendant may be released.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="grievance" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A complaint filed against an attorney or judge, claiming an ethics violation.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="violation" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> An offense for which the only sentence authorized is a fine.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="broken down irretrievably" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The most common reason for granting a divorce. It means there is no hope of the husband and wife getting back together again. Also known as "no-fault" divorce.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jurisdiction" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the geographical, subject matter, and monetary limitations of a court. Personal jurisdiction- Directed to a specific person to impose a personal liability on him (usually the defendant).  Subject matter jurisdiction- Topic of consideration, thing in dispute, right claimed by one party against another</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="estop" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> to stop, bar, or impede</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="bail" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the security given (or posted) to ensure the future appearance of a defendant</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="at issue" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> whenever the parties to a suit come to a point in the pleadings which is affirmed on one side and denied on the other, they are said to be "at issue"</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="acquit" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the act of freeing a person from the charge of an offense by means of a decision, verdict or other legal process; to discharge</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="delinquent" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> In civil or family cases, failing to pay an amount of money when due</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="title" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Legal recognition of the ownership of property, usually proven by a document.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="central transportation unit" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Persons in the Division of Juvenile Detention Services who provide safe and secure transportation services for juveniles detained at Juvenile Detention Centers, Alternative Detention Program and Girls’ Detention Program.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="change of venue" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the removal of a suit begun in one county or district to another county or district for trial, though the term may also apply to the removal of a suit from one court to another court of the same county or district</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="transfer hearing" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Juvenile Court hearing to determine whether a child, 14 or older, charged with a serious juvenile offense should have his/her case transferred to a criminal court and be subject to the same processes and penalties as an adult charged with the same crime.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="equitable action (equity matter)" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an action which may be brought for the purpose of restraining the threatened infliction of wrongs or injuries, and the prevention of threatened illegal action; case in which payment of money damages will not be adequate compensation</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="juror" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Member of a jury.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="count" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The different parts of a complaint, which could each be a basis or grounds for the lawsuit.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="examination before trial (ebt)" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a formal interrogation of parties and witnesses before trial</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="mistrial" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a trial which has been terminated and declared void prior to the reaching of verdict due to extraordinary circumstance, serious prejudicial misconduct or hung jury - it does not result in a judgment for any party but merely indicates a failure of trial</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="plaintiff" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the party bringing a civil action</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="civil action" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A lawsuit other than a criminal case usually filed in a Judicial District courthouse. Includes family actions (divorces, child support, etc) and small claims cases, although these are both separately designated.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="order to detain" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> An order signed by a judge of the Superior Court authorizing admission of a juvenile to a Juvenile Detention Center, pending a hearing on the next business day.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="detention hearing or detention release hearing" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A hearing on the first business day after a juvenile is admitted to juvenile detention concerning the legality and appropriateness of continued detention of the juvenile. The detention decision must be reviewed at least every fifteen days.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="conservator" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> one who is appointed by a court to manage the affairs of a protected person</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="bar" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> 1. Prohibit - to bar the prosecution of an action. 2. The members of the legal profession.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="legal aid or legal services" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Free legal representatives in civil cases for income eligible persons. Call 1-800-453-3320 to apply.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="short form order" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an order prepared by the court</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="surety bond" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The court requires cash, real estate or a professional bail bondpersons signature as collateral before releasing the defendant back into the community. (The court may allow the defendant to post ten percent of the bond in cash to secure his or her release.)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="equitable distribution" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the power to distribute equitably upon divorce all property legally and beneficially acquired during marriage by husband and wife or either of them, whether legal title lies in their joint or individual names</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="hung jury" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a jury whose members cannot reconcile their differences of opinion and thus cannot reach a verdict</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="allegation" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the assertion, declaration, or statement of a party to an action, made in a pleading, setting out what the party expects to prove</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="juvenile transportation officer" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Also called JTO. A person who provides safe transportation services for juveniles in custody.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="juvenile delinquent" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A person under the age of 16 who commits a criminal act.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="emancipated minor" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A person under the legal majority age of 18 who is granted most rights and legal privileges of an adult (C.G.S.§46b-150, et seq.).</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="date-stamp" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the stamping on a document of the date it is received</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="opening statement" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the first address of counsel prior to offering of evidence</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="stipulation" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an agreement by attorneys on opposite sides of a case as to any matter pertaining to the proceedings or trial - most stipulations must be in writing</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="oral proof" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> evidence given by word of mouth; the oral testimony of a witness</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="custody affidavit" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A sworn statement containing facts about a child involved in a case, including full name of the child, date of birth, current and past residences and other information as may be required by law.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="seal" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> to close a case file from public scrutiny - in instances of youthful offenders and acquittal, sealing orders are issued by the court to prevent the public from obtaining information on the cases</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="subpoena duces tecum (judicial)" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an order issued by the court requiring a person to produce specified documents or records in a trial</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="calendar" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a schedule of matters to be heard in court</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="with prejudice" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the term, as applied to judgment of dismissal, is as conclusive of rights of parties as if action had been prosecuted to final adjudication adverse to the plaintiff</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="revocation hearing" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A hearing held before a judge to determine whether or not a person has violated the conditions of probation. If there is a finding that a violation has occurred, the judge may impose all or part of the original sentence.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="family violence education program" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A program for family violence offenders that if successfully completed, results in the dismissal of criminal charges.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="compensatory damages" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> reimbursement for actual loss or injury, as distinguished from exemplary or punitive damages</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="military calendar" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> To hold in suspense an action that cannot reasonably be tried because a party or witness is in the military service.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="special master" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a special master is an attorney appointed on an ad hoc basis to assist the court in hearing motions (NYS)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="amicus curiae" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> A Friend of the Court. A non-party to a proceeding that the Court permits to present its views.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="guardian" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A person who has the power and duty to take care of another person and/or to manage the property and rights of another person who is considered incapable of taking care of his or her personal affairs.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="discovery" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A formal request by one party in a lawsuit to disclose information or facts known by other parties or witnesses.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="notice of petition" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Written notice of a petitioner that a hearing will be held in a court to determine the relief requested in an annexed petition.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="polling the jury" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a practice whereby the jurors are asked individually whether they assented, and still assent, to the verdict</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="felony" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Any criminal offense for which a person may be sentenced to a term of imprisonment of more than of one year.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="substance abuse education" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A community based program for drug offenders that provides education about the harmful effects of drug abuse and also supervises community service.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="third-party action" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> A claim asserted by a defendant, styled a third-party plaintiff, against a person, styled a third-party defendant.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="mandamus" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> An order directed to a private corporation, or any of its officers, or to an executive, administrative or judicial officer, or to a lower court, commanding the performance of a particular act.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="sum certain" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Liquidated damages pursuant to contract, promissory note, law, etc.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="without prejudice" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a dismissal "without prejudice" allows a new suit to be brought on the same cause of action</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="eminent domain" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the power to take private property for public use by condemnation, i.e., the legal process by which real estate of a private owner is taken for public use without the owner's consent, but upon the award and payment of just compensation</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="execution suspended" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A prison sentence that is suspended in whole or in part provided certain conditions of probation or conditional discharge are met by the defendant.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="contract" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a legally enforceable agreement between two or more persons or parties (oral or written)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="housing specialist" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A person who provides pretrial mediation of landlord/tenant cases to reach settlement. Also provides information about community resources to litigants.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ejectment" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A legal case filed against someone who is a holdover tenant (someone who remains after the expiration of a lease).</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="legal age" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Eighteen (18) years of age. See CPLR Section 1206.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="satisfaction" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Discharge of a legal obligation, as in a "Satisfaction of Judgment."</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in rem" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Regarding the right or title to property.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="litigant" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Party to a legal action</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="remittitur" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> legal process by which an appellate court transmits to the court below the proceedings before it, together with its decision, for such further action and entry of judgment as is required by the decision of the appellate court</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="custody" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A court order deciding where a child will live and how decisions about the child will be made. Parents may ask for any custody arrangement that they believe is in the best interest of their child.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="movant" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the party who initiates the motion</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="appellee" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the party against whom an appeal is taken</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="intestate" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a person who dies without a will</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="certify" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> to testify in writing</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="crime victim compensation program" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Awards money to crime victims and their families for medical, mental health, dental, funeral expenses, lost wages and loss of support.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="diversionary programs" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Community based programs that are used to keep eligible, convicted criminal offenders out of prison.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="maintenance" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the furnishing by one person to another the means of living, or food, clothing, shelter, etc., particularly where the legal relations of the parties is such that one is bound to support the other, as between parent and child or between spouses</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="security for costs" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> An undertaking required by a court to cover the payment of costs if the judgment is against the depositor.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="court of limited jurisdiction" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> A City Court, District Court or other court that has jurisdiction only over actions authorized by law.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="chattel" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> article of personal property</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="referee" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a person to whom a cause pending in a court is referred by the court to take testimony, hear the parties, and report thereon to the court, or to make a judicial determination - the referee is an officer exercising judicial powers and is an arm of the court for a specific purpose</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jd - judicial district" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Connecticut has 13 judicial districts (JD) in which civil, criminal, family and juvenile matters are heard. Civil jury, civil non-jury, administrative appeals and family matters generally are heard in a JD courthouse. </description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="serious juvenile offense" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Certain criminal offenses listed in the Connecticut General Statutes, which are crimes against persons, serious property crimes and certain drug offenses. A juvenile charged with a Serious Juvenile Offense by police may be admitted to a Juvenile Detention Center with a prior court order and may be released only by order of a judge of the Superior Court.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="counter claim" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A claim by the defendant in a civil action that the defendant is entitled to damages or other relief from the plaintiff.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="impleader" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> An addition of a third party to an action by the defendant.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="declaration" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> An unsworn statement of facts made by a party to the transaction, or by one who has an interest in the facts recounted.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="legal aid" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> system by which legal services are rendered to those in financial need who cannot afford private counsel</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pre-sentence investigation" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Also called PSI. A background investigation conducted by a probation officer on a person who has been convicted of a criminal offense.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="dismissal without prejudice" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Action dismissed, not on the merits, which may be re-instituted.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="affirm" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an act of declaring something to be true under the penalty of perjury by a person who conscientiously declines to take an oath for religious or other pertinent reasons</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="amend" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> To change.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="adult court transfer" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The transfer of juveniles who are at least fourteen years old to regular criminal dockets in Geographical Area or Judicial District courts. Also involves the transfer from a Juvenile Detention Center to the State Department of Correction.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="appearance" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the participation in the proceedings by a party summoned in an action, either in person or through an attorney</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="trial referee" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> An attorney appointed by the Chief Justice to hear any civil non-jury case where the parties agree to use a trial referee and all the legal papers have been filed.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="et al" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an abbreviation of et alia meaning "and others"</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="juris number" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> An identification number assigned to each attorney in Connecticut.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="peremptory challenge" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the challenge which may be used to reject a certain number of prospective jurors without assigning any reason</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="prosecutor" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Also called the state's attorney. Represents the state in a criminal case against a defendant.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ready" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Means ready to start the trial or begin oral argument. Usually said by an attorney or party in response to a judge calling the list of scheduled cases.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="victim services advocate" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A person who assesses a victim’s needs and helps the victim understand the court case, how to exercise their rights and how to access other resources.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="notice of entry" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> A notice with an affidavit of service stating that the attached copy of an entered order or judgment has been served by a party on another party.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="sine die" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Without a date, as in an action being adjourned sine die. Legal process which commands a witness to appear and testify.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="serious juvenile offender" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A child who has been adjudicated by the juvenile court for a serious juvenile offense.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="inquest" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a proceeding which usually is a limited non-jury trial for the purpose of fixing the amount of damages where the plaintiff or defendant alone introduces testimony.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="remand" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> to send a case back from an appellate court to the lower court from which it came, for further proceedings</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pendente lite order" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A court order made before final orders are granted.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="damages" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Monetary compensation or indemnity for wrong or injury caused by the violation of a legal right. 1. Compensatory damages - Reimbursement for actual loss or injury. 2. Exemplary damages - Monetary award by way of punishment for injury caused by aggravated circumstances or malice, in addition to compensation for the injury. 3. Punitive damages - Monetary compensation awarded in excess of ordinary damages, as punishment for a gross wrong.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="modification" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Request to change a prior order. Usually requires showing a change in circumstances since the date of the prior order.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="party" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Person having a direct interest in a legal matter, transaction or proceeding.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pleadings" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> complaint or petition, answer, and reply</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="http" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description>//www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="clerk's extract" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a summary of a trial which is written by a clerk</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="income withholding order" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A court order to deduct child support or alimony payments from someone's wages. All child support court orders must include an income withholding order unless both parents ask the judge not to.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="failure to appear" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> In a civil case, failing to file an Appearance form. In a criminal case, failing to come to court for a scheduled hearing.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="incarceration" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Confinement to a state correctional institute or prison.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="capital felony" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A criminal offense in which the death penalty may be imposed (C.G.S. '53a-54b).</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="individual assignment system (ias)" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a system, established for all civil actions and proceedings heard in Supreme and County Court, which provides for the continuous supervision of each action and proceeding by a single judge (NYS)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="judgment" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> A determination of the rights of the parties in an action or special proceeding. A judgment shall refer to and state the result of a verdict or decision, or recite the circumstances on which it is based</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="legal custody" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Relationship with a child created by court order which gives a person legal responsibility for the physical possession of a minor and the duty to protect, care for and discipline the child.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="acknowledgement" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The signature of a clerk or attorney certifying that the person filing the document has sworn that the contents are true, and/or that the document is signed by his or her free act and deed.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="costs" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> The statutory sum awarded to the successful party when a judgment is entered. (Section 1901 all Court Acts.)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="guardian ad litem" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> person appointed by a court to represent a minor or incompetent for purpose of some litigation</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="relief" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Legal remedy</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="no fault divorce" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The most common kind of divorce, where no one needs to prove that the husband or the wife is at fault, or caused the marriage to end. Described as "broken down irretrievably".</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="court reporter" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a person who transcribes by shorthand or stenographically takes down testimony during court proceedings</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="docket" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a document which summarizes a case</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="non seq. (non sequitur)" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> It does not follow</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ad damnum" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> clause of a pleading alleging amount of loss or injury</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="et ano" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> And another.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="contested action" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an action which involves disputed issue(s) of fact or law</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="negligence" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> conduct which falls below the standard established by law for the protection of others against unreasonable risk of harm</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="automatic orders" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Court orders that take effect when a divorce or custody case is started.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="rest" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> To be done presenting the evidence in a case, as in "the plaintiff rests".</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="alimony" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Money a court requires one spouse to pay the other spouse for support before and/or after the divorce is granted. If you do not ask for alimony at the final hearing, you can never get it in the future.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="habeas corpus" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> "You have the body." - the name given a variety of writs whose object is to bring a person before a court or judge - in most common usage, it is directed to the official or person detaining another, commanding him/her to produce the body of a person detained so the court may determine if such person has been denied his/her liberty without due process of law</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="summary process" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> An eviction case.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="domicile" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> that place where a person has a true and permanent home - a person may have several residences, but only one domicile</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="bench" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> The Judge's seat or the judge, himself/herself, (e.g., the attorney addressed the bench)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="appellant" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the party who takes an appeal to a higher court</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="arrest" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> When a person is taken into custody by a police officer and charged with a crime.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="affinity" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Related by marriage; family relation from one's spouse's family.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="discovery (or disclosure)" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a proceeding whereby one party to an action may be informed as to facts known by other parties or witnesses</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="warrant" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a written order directing the arrest of a person issued by an authority - warrants are "issued," "executed" or "canceled"</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="alternate juror" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a juror selected as substitute in case another juror must leave the jury panel</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="complaint" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the initial pleading in an action formally setting forth the facts and reasons on which the demand for relief is based</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="nunc pro tunc" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> (now for then) presently considered as if occurring at an earlier date; effective retroactively</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="community service" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Work that convicted defendants are required to perform in order to repay the community for the harm caused to the community by the crime.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="condemnation" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> see eminent domain</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="judge" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A person who hears and decides cases for the courts. Appointed by the governor for a term of eight years and confirmed by the General Assembly.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="execution" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> (1) the performance of all acts necessary to render a written instrument complete, such as signing, sealing, acknowledging, and delivering the instruments (2) supplementary proceedings to enforce a judgment, which, if monetary, involves a direction to the sheriff to take the necessary steps to collect the judgment</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="bill of costs" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> A written statement of the itemized taxable costs and disbursements</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="expunge" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the authorized act of physically destroying information, in files, computers or other depositories</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="posting bond" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> To pay the court ordered bond amount with cash or property.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="eviction" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Legally forcing a tenant out of rented property. (Housing Publications)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="special referee (or referee)" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the special referee has the authority to exercise judicial functions when assigned duties by the court to determine the following (1) to determine an issue (binding) (2) to perform an act (disclosure) (3) to hear and report - matrimonial actions may be included (NYS)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="adjudicatory hearing" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Juvenile court proceeding to determine whether the allegations made in a petition are true and whether the child/youth should be subject to orders of the court.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="order of detention (detention order)" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> An order issued by a judge of the Superior Court finding that there is probable cause that a juvenile committed an offense or a violation of a court order and ordering that the juvenile be held in a Juvenile Detention Center or some alternative facility until further order of the court.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="index number" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a number issued by the county clerk, which is used to identify a case - in civil matters there is usually a charge</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="honor court" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A program of outpatient group therapy for alcohol abusers.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="minute book" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> A Court Clerk's Journal of Courtroom proceedings.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="sua sponte" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> upon its own motion, initiation or will; without a prior request</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="court clerk" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The person who maintains the official court record of your case. The court clerks’ office receives all court papers and assigns hearing dates.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="family violence victim advocate" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A person who works with domestic violence victims to determine their needs and inform them of their rights and resources available to them.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="restraining order" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A civil court order to protect a family or household member from physical abuse.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="corroborate" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> to strengthen; to add weight by additional evidence</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="vacate" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> to set aside a previous action</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="fiduciary" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a person or institution who manages money or property for another, and who must exercise a standard of care in such management activity imposed by law or contract</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="indigent" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Someone without enough money to either support himself or herself or his or her family. Someone who cannot afford to pay certain fees required by the court. (Civil, Family, Housing | Juvenile)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="res judicata" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a thing judicially acted upon or decided</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="proceeding" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the succession of events constituting the process by which judicial action is invoked and utilized pursuant to procedure</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="summons (juvenile)" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A written notice issued by the court commanding a person to appear in a court at a given date and time. A summons is issued to an individual charged or other party on a petition or complaint.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="court-appointed attorney" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> An attorney who is asked by the court (judge) to either represent a party to the case, or to serve in some other capacity that the case requires.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="decision" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the determination reached by a court in any judicial proceeding, which is the basis of the judgment</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="violation of probation" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Action or inaction that disobeys a condition of probation.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="classification and program officer" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Also called CPO. A person who provides classification, program, counseling and recreational services to detained juveniles. May attend certain court hearings in Juvenile Matters and provide reports.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="moot" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> (adj.) unsettled, undecided, not necessary to be decided</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jury charge" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The judge's formal instructions on the law to the jury before it begins deliberations.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="orders of temporary custody" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Also called an OTC. Court order placing a child or youth in the short-term legal custody of an individual or agency authorized to care for juveniles.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="certified copy" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Copy of a document signed and certified as a true copy of an original by the Clerk of the Court or other authorized persons (e.g., lawyer).</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="child support" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Money paid by a parent to help meet the financial needs of a child. </description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="mitigating circumstances" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Circumstances that may be considered to reduce the guilt of a defendant. Usually based on fairness or mercy.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="supplementary proceedings" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> further inquiry, under court jurisdiction, after entry of judgment, to determine means for enforcing the judgment against judgment debtor</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="judicial hearing officer (jho)" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a person who has served as a judge or justice of a court of record of the Unified Court System, and who no longer is serving in such capacity, except a person who was removed from a judicial position pursuant to Section 22 of Article VI of the Constitution</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="probable cause hearing" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A hearing held before a judge in criminal cases to determine if enough evidence exists to prosecute. The probable cause hearing must be conducted within 60 days of the filing of the complaint or information in Superior Court, unless the accused person waives the time or the court grants an extension based on good cause.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="court monitor" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The person who prepares a written record of the court hearing for a fee, if requested, from audiotapes made during the hearing.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="garnishment" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A court order to collect money or property. For example, a garnishment may be issued to an employer to pay part of an employee’s wages to someone else to pay a debt or judgment.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="unconditional discharge" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A sentence in a criminal case in which the defendant is released without imprisonment, probation supervision or conditions.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="interrogatory" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Formal, written questions used to get information from another party in a lawsuit.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="cgs" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Abbreviation for Connecticut General Statutes  External Link - You are leaving the CT Judicial Branch website</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="case file" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the court file containing papers submitted in a case</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="adversary" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> An opponent. The defendant is the plaintiff's adversary.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="garnishee" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> A person who owes a debt to a judgment debtor, or a person other than the judgment debtor who has property in his/her possession or custody in which a judgment debtor has an interest</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="residential treatment programs" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Programs that provide extensive drug or alcohol treatment on an inpatient basis.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="conditional discharge" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A disposition, in criminal cases, where the defendant must satisfy certain court-ordered conditions instead of a prison term.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="full faith and credit" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> A requirement of the U.S. Constitution that the records and judicial proceedings of one state shall have the same effect in courts of other states with the same jurisdiction.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="testimony" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an oral declaration made by a witness or party under oath</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="marshal" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The persons responsible for courthouse security including the metal detectors at the entrance of each courthouse and maintaining order in each courtroom. A marshal can also serve (give copies of) legal papers to the other people named in a lawsuit.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="information (the)" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> In a criminal case, the formal court document in the clerk's file, which contains the charges, dates of offenses, bond status, continuance dates and disposition.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="respondent" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> One who formally answers the allegations stated in a petition which has been filed with the court. Also known as a defendant in a civil action</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="infraction" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A case where the fine may be paid by mail and usually the person does not have to appear or come to court. For example, a speeding ticket. (Infractions Schedule)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="lien" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a claim upon the property of another as security for some debt</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="commitment" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an order to commit a person to the custody of a sheriff, commissioner of corrections, or mental health facility</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="arraignment" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The first court appearance of a person accused of a crime. The person is advised of his or her rights by a judge and may respond to the criminal charges by entering a plea. Usually happens the morning after a person is arrested.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="parties" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The people or legal entities that are named as plaintiff(s) and defendant(s) on legal papers.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="sentence modification" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A defendant’s written application to the sentencing judge or court to reduce the sentence at any time during the sentence. The judge conducts a hearing. If the original sentence was more than three years, the prosecutor must agree.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="deponent" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> One who testifies under oath to the truth of facts.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="transfer" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the removal of a cause from the jurisdiction of one court or judge to another by lawful authority</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="fair preponderance" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Level of proof in a civil action; more than half; more convincing.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="foreperson" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a member of a jury, usually the first juror called and sworn, or a juror elected by fellow jurors, who delivers the verdict to the court</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="annulment" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A court order declaring that a marriage is invalid.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="alcohol education program" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A pre-trial program for first time offenders charged with driving a motor vehicle under the influence of alcohol.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="suit" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> A legal action or proceeding.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="juvenile detention officer" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Also called JDO. A person who works within a Juvenile Detention Center.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="cause of action" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> grounds on which a legal action may be brought (e.g., property damage, personal injury, goods sold and delivered, work labor and services).</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="visitation" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A court order deciding the amount of time a non-custodial parent may spend with his or her child, also called parenting time or access.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="adversary system" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the system of trial practice in the U.S. and some other countries in which each of the opposing, or adversary, parties has full opportunity to present and establish its opposing contentions before the court</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="power of attorney" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> instrument authorizing one to act legally for another either generally or in a specified matter</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="bill of particulars" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> factual detail submitted by a claimant after a request by the adverse party which details, clarifies or explains further the charges and/or facts alleged in a pleading</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="estoppel" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a rule of law which prevents a person from alleging or denying a fact, because of his/her own previous act</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="bench warrant" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Court papers issued by the judge, "from the bench," for the arrest of a person.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="contempt of court" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an act or omission tending to obstruct or interfere with the orderly administration of justice or to impair the dignity of the court or respect for its authority</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="juvenile matters" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> All cases concerning uncared for, neglected or dependent children and youth, termination of parental rights of children committed to a state agency, matters concerning families with service needs, contested matters involving termination of parental rights or removal of guardian transferred from the Probate Court and the emancipation of minors. It does not include guardianship or adoption cases, or matters affecting property rights of any child or youth over which the Probate Court has jurisdiction. The Probate Court hears appeals concerning adoption, termination of parental rights and removal of a parent as guardian are included. Juvenile matters in the criminal session include all cases concerning delinquent children in the state.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="bail bondsperson" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A person who lends money to a defendant to pay for bail.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="counsel" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Lawyer or attorney.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="moving party" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The person making the request to the court in a case.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="education program" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A program for family violence offenders that, if granted and successfully completed, results in dismissal of criminal charges (C.G.S. §46b-38c).</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="default" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a "default" in an action of law occurs when a defendant omits to plead or otherwise defend within the time allowed, or fails to appear at the trial</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="record" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The pleadings, the exhibits and the transcript made by the court reporter of all proceedings in a trial.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="court interpreter" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The person who translates court hearings from English to another language. Provided at state expense in all criminal cases and in cases enforcing child support orders, if requested. No interpreter is available for divorce or any other civil case.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="cip" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Children in Placement- a voluntary program in Juvenile Court, which monitors neglect, cases.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="verification" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> confirmation of the correctness, truth or authenticity of pleading, account or other paper by an affidavit or oath</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="interlocutory" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> provisional; temporary; not final - refers to orders and decrees of a court</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="minutes" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a record of court proceedings kept by noting significant events</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jury (advisory)" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a body of jurors impaneled to hear a case in which the parties have no right to a jury trial - the judge remains solely responsible for the findings and may accept or reject the jury's verdict</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="deliberation" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the process by which a panel of jurors comes to a decision on a verdict</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="citation" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> 1) summons to appear; 2) reference to authorities in support of an argument</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="evidence" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a form of proof or probative matter legally presented at the trial of an issue by the acts of the parties and through witnesses, records, documents, concrete objects, etc., for the purpose of inducing belief in the minds of the court or the jury</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="complex litigation" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> A specialized docket designed for complex civil cases, where one judge hears the case from beginning to end. Criteria includes</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pretrial" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> In a civil case, a conference with a judge or trial referee to discuss discovery and settlement. In a criminal case, a conference with the prosecutor, defense attorney and judge to discuss the case status and what will happen next.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="law librarian" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Court staff who maintain legal reference and research materials for public use.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="adjudicate" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> to hear or try and determine judicially</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="dissolution of marriage" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> the effect of a judgment of dissolution of marriage is to restore the parties to the state of unmarried persons</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="slip opinions" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Opinions, or written decisions, of the Supreme Court or the Appellate Court that are publicly released prior to their official publication in the Connecticut Law Journal.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="best interest of the child" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> The standard a judge uses to decide custody and visitation issues.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="nolo contendere" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> It means "no contest". A plea in a criminal case that allows the defendant to be convicted without admitting guilt for the crime charged. Although a finding of guilty is entered on the criminal court record; the defendant can deny the charges in a civil action based on the same acts.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="post judgment" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Any request to a court or action by a judge after a judgment in a case.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="interpleader" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> action by which one having possession of an article or fund claimed by two parties may compel them to litigate the title between themselves, instead of with him/her</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="inter alia" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Among other things.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="accelerated rehabilitation" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Also called AR. A program that gives persons charged with a crime or motor vehicle violation for the first time a second chance. The person is placed on probation for up to two years. If probation is completed satisfactorily, the charges are dismissed.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="states attorney" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> An attorney who represents the state in criminal cases. The prosecutor.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="juvenile detention" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> State facility to provide for the temporary care of a child who alleged to be delinquent and who requires a physically restricted, secure environment.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="restore/ reinstate to calendar" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> to reinstate the action to active inventory</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="stay" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a stopping or suspension of procedure or execution by judicial or executive order</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="uncared for" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Legal description of a child or youth who is homeless or whose home cannot provide the specialized care which his/her physical, emotional or mental condition requires.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="natural person" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> Individual (does not include corporate entities)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="substitute charge" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> In a criminal case, a charge that replaces the original charge by the prosecutor.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="financial affidavit" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Short | Long - A sworn statement of income, expenses, property (called assets) and debts (called liabilities).</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="show cause" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an order, decree, execution, etc., to appear as directed, and present to the court such reasons and considerations as one has to offer why it should not be confirmed, take effect, be executed, or as the case may be</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="summary judgment" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a determination in an action on the grounds that there is no genuine issue of fact</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="affidavit" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a sworn or affirmed statement made in writing and signed; if sworn, it is notarized</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="special term" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> a court part set aside to hear specific types of cases</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="parole" ref="http://www.jud.ct.gov/legalterms.htm">
<description> Release from incarceration after serving part of a sentence.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="precedent" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> previously adjudged action or decision on same or similar point, serving as a rule or example for present guidance</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="waiver" ref="http://www.nycourts.gov/lawlibraries/glossary.shtml">
<description> an intentional and voluntary relinquishment of some known right</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="iudex non calculat" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A principle that calculation errors made by the court do not invalidate the judgement on a technicality. Also taken to mean that the judge does not tally up the arguments of both sides and decide in favor of the more numerous, but rather weighs all of the evidence without regard to the number of arguments made.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="fiat justitia et pereat mundus" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Often used as a motto, notably by Ferdinand I, Holy Roman Emperor.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="non obstante verdicto" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A circumstance where the judge may override the jury verdict and reverse or modify the decision.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="non constat" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to information given by one who is not supposed to give testimony, such as an attorney bringing up new information that did not come from a witness. Such information is typically nullified.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="non compos mentis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>not having mental capacity to perform some legal act</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="lis pendens" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Often used in the context of public announcements of legal proceedings to come.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="quasi" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Resembling or being similar to something, without actually being that thing.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ergo" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Therefore</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="sub modo" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Term in contract law that allows limited modifications to a contract after the original form has been agreed to by all parties.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="lex scripta" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Law that specifically codifies something, as opposed to common law or customary law.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="lex specialis derogat legi generali" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Where several laws apply to the same situation, the more specific one(s) take precedence over more general ones.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="intra legem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used in various contexts to refer to the legal foundation for a thing.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="sub silentio" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A ruling, order, or other court action made without specifically stating the ruling, order, or action. The effect of the ruling or action is implied by related and subsequent actions, but not specifically stated.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex proprio motu" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Commonly spoken as "by one's own accord."</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="prout patet per recordum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used to cite something that has already been admitted into the record.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="persona non grata" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A person who is officially considered unwelcome by a host country in which they are residing in a diplomatic capacity. The person is typically expelled to their home country.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="per capita" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>dividing money up strictly and equally according to the number of beneficiaries</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="audi alteram partem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to the idea that one cannot be fairly judged unless the cases for and against them have been heard.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="de lege ferenda" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used in the context of "how the law should be", such as for proposed legislation.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jus commune" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Not actually referring to common law, this term refers to common facets of civil law that underlie all aspects of the law.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="per se" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Something that is, as a matter of law.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="scire facias" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A writ, directing local officials to officially inform a party of official proceedings concerning them.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="doli incapax" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Presumption that young children or persons with diminished mental capacity cannot form the intent to commit a crime.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="corpus juris" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The complete collection of laws of a particular jurisdiction or court.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex cathedra" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Where chair refers to authority or position. Authority derived from one's position.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ratio scripta" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The popular opinion of Roman law, held by those in the Medieval period.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pro rata" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A calculation adjusted based on a proportional value relevant to the calculation. An example would be a tenant being charged a portion of a month's rent based on having lived there less than a full month. The amount charged would be proportional to the time occupied.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="non faciat malum, ut inde veniat bonum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Performing some illegal action is not excused by the fact that a positive result came therefrom. Often used to argue that some forms of expression, such as graffiti or pornographic films, cannot be given the protection of law (e.g. copyright) as they are or may be considered illegal or morally reprehensible.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="nudum pactum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>An unenforceable promise, due to the absence of consideration or value exchanged for the promise.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="fructus industriales" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>In property law, a co-owner profting from her or his fructus industriales is solely responsible for any losses that my occur.[2]</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in pari delicto" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used when both parties to a case are equally at fault.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="noscitur a sociis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>An ambiguous word or term can be clarified by considering the whole context in which it is used, without having to define the term itself.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="restitutio in integrum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>(1) Restoration of something, such as a building or damaged property, to its original condition. (2) In contract law, when considering breach of contract and remedies, to restore a party to an original position.[3]</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex parte" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A decision reached, or case brought, by or for one party without the other party being present.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="cogitationis poenam nemo patitur" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Nobody suffers punishment for mere intent</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="mutatis mutandis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A caution to a reader when using one example to illustrate a related but slightly different situation. The caution is that the reader must adapt the example to change what is needed for it to apply to the new situation.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="exempli gratia" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Usually abbreviated "e.g.".</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="animus possidendi" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>"In order to claim possessory rights, an individual must establish physical control of the res and the intention to possess (i.e. animus possidendi)"[2]</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="deorum injuriae diis curae" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Blasphemy is a crime against the State, rather than against God.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jus primae noctis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Supposed right of the lord of an estate to take the virginity of women in his estate on their wedding night.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="statu quo" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>In contract law, in a case of innocent representation, the injured party is entitled to be replaced in statu quo. Note the common usage is status quo from the Latin status quo ante, the "state in which before" or "the state of affairs that existed previously."</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="cui bono" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Suggests that the perpetrator(s) of a crime can often be found by investigating those who would have benefited financially from the crime, even if it is not immediately obvious.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex concessis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Often used in a "guilt by association" context.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="defalcation" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Misappropriation of funds by one entrusted with them.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pro hac vice" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to a lawyer who is allowed to participate (only) in a specific case, despite being in a jurisdiction in which he has not been generally admitted</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="fortis attachiamentum, validior praesumptionem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>When determining whether a chattel is a fixture: "size doesn't matter, how much or degree chattel is attached to 'land' and to 'what' "</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex aequo et bono" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Usually defined as "what is right and good." Used to describe the power of a judge or arbiter to consider only what is fair and good for the specific case, and not necessarily what the law may require. In courts, usually only done if all parties agree.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="de lege lata" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Concerning the law as it exists, without consideration of how things should be.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="terra nullius" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Land that has never been part of a sovereign state, or land which a sovereign state has relinquished claim to.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="sui generis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Something that is unique amongst a group.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="et uxor" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Usually used instead of naming a man's wife as a party in a case.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="lex communis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Alternate form of jus commune. Refers to common facets of civil law that underlie all aspects of the law.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="non est factum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A method whereby a signatory to a contract can invalidate it by showing that his signature to the contract was made unintentionally or without full understanding of the implications.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in curia" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Conducted in open court. The opposite of in camera.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jurat" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Appears at the end of an affidavit, where the party making the affirmation signs the oath, and the information on whom the oath was sworn before is placed.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in propria persona" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Alternate form of in prope persona. One who represents themselves in court without the [official] assistance of an attorney.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jus naturale" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Laws common to all people, that the average person would find reasonable, regardless of their nationality.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="nisi prius" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to the court of original jurisdiction in a given matter.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jura novit curia" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Concept that parties to a case do not need to define how the law applies to their case. The court is solely responsible for determining what laws apply.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="et seq." ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Abbreviation of et sequens, meaning "and the following ones". Used in citations to indicate that the cited portion extends to the pages following the cited page.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="volenti non fit injuria" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Notion that a person cannot bring a claim against another for injury, if said person willingly placed themselves in a situation where they knew injury could result.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ad infinitum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>To continue forever.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in re" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used in the title of a decision or comment to identify the matter they are related to.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="locus in quo" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The location where a cause of action arose.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="cuius est solum eius est usque ad coelum et ad inferos" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used in reference to the rights of property owners to the air above, and land below, their property.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="certiorari" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A type of writ seeking judicial review.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="animus nocendi" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The subjective state of mind of the author of a crime, with reference to the exact knowledge of illegal content of his behaviour, and of its possible consequences.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="suo motu" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to a court or other official agency taking some action on its own accord. Similar tosua sponte.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="rationae soli" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>"Certain rights may arise by virtue of ownership of the soil upon which wild animals are found."[2]</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jus sanguinis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Social law concept wherein citizenship of a nation is determined by having one or both parents being citizens.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="quantum valebant" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Under Common Law, i.e. a remedy to compute reasonable damages when a contract has been breached—the implied promise of payment of a reasonable price for goods. In contract law, for requirements of consideration, reasonable worth for goods delivered. Usage: quantum meruit has replaced quantum valebant in consideration;[3] in the case of contract remedy, quantum valebant is being used less, and could be considered to be obsolete.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="supersedeas" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A bond tendered by an appellant as surety to the court, requesting a delay of payment for awards or damages granted, pending the outcome of the appeal.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="motion in limine" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Motions offered at the start of a trial, often to suppress or pre-allow certain evidence or testimony.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="trial de novo" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A completely new trial of a matter previously judged. It specifically refers to a replacement trial for the previous one, and not an appeal of the previous decision.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="nemo judex in sua causa" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Prevents conflict of interest in courts. Often invoked when there is really no conflict, but when there is even the appearance of one.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="sic utere tuo ut alienum non laedas" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>While an individual is entitled to the use and enjoyment of one's estate, the right is not without limits. Restrictions can give rise to tort actions include trespass, negligence, strict liability, and nuisance.[2]</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="viz." ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Namely</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="erratum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Having been made in error.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="inter vivos" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to a gift or other non-sale transfer between living parties. This is in contrast to a will, where the transfer takes effect upon one party's death.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="caveat" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>When used by itself, refers to a qualification, or warning.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="res publica" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>All things subject to concern by the citizenry. The root of the word republic.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="nemo debet esse iudex in propria" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>In the past it was thought that it included just two rules namely (1) nemo debet esse judex in propria causa (no one shall be a judge in his own case)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="situs" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used to refer to laws specific to the location where specific property exists, or where an offense or tort was committed.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="indicia" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Often used in copyright notices. Refers to distinctive markings that identify a piece of intellectual property.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="hostis humani generis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A party considered to be the enemy of all nations, such as maritime pirates.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="de bonis asportatis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Specifies that larceny was taking place in addition to any other crime named. E.g. "trespass de bonis asportatis".</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="mare clausum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A body of water under the jurisdiction of a state or nation, to which access is not permitted, or is tightly regulated.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="sine qua non" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to some essential event or action, without which there can be no specified consequence.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pro se" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Representing oneself, without counsel. Also known as pro per representation.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="novus actus interveniens" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>a break in causation (and therefore probably liability) because something else has happened to remove the causal link</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in loco parentis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used to refer to a person or entity assuming the normal parental responsibilities for a minor. This can be used in transfers of legal guardianship, or in the case of schools or other institutions that act in the place of the parents on a day-to-day basis.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="quod est necessarium est licitum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>What is necessary is lawful</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="probatio vincit praesumptionem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>proof overcomes presumption</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="lex lata" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The law as it has been enacted</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="quaere" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used in legal drafts to call attention to some uncertainty or inconsistency in the material being cited.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="consuetudo pro lege servatur" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Where no laws apply to a given situation, the customs of the place and time will have the force of law.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="fumus boni iuris" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to having a sufficient legal basis to bring legal action.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ab initio" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>"Commonly used referring to the time a contract, statute, marriage, or deed become legal. e.g The couple was covered ab initio by her health policy."[1]</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex gratia" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Something done voluntarily and with no expectation a legal liability arising therefrom.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="scire feci" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The official response of the official serving a writ of scire facias, informing the court that the writ has been properly delivered.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in articulo mortis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Often used in probate law, as well as for testimony in the sense of a dying declaration.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="actus reus" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Part of what proves criminal liability (with mens rea)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex post facto law" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A retroactive law. E.g. a law that makes a past act illegal that was not illegal when it was done.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="de bonis non administratis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Assets of an estate remaining after the death (or removal) of the designated estate administrator. An "administrator de bonis non administratis" will then be appointed to dispose of these goods.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="prima facie" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A matter that appears to be sufficiently based in the evidence as to be considered true.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="facio ut facias" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A type of contract wherein one party agrees to do work for the other, in order that the second party can then perform some work for the first in exchange.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pendente lite" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Court orders used to provide relief until the final judgement is rendered. Commonly used in divorce proceedings.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="nolle prosequi" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A statement from the prosecution that they are voluntarily discontinuing (or will not initiate) prosecution of a matter.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="corpus juris gentium" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The complete collection of international law.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="vice versa" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Something that is the same either way.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="nullum crimen, nulla poena sine praevia lege poenali" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>One cannot be prosecuted for doing something that was not prohibited by law at the time and place it was committed, notwithstanding laws made since that time. A form of prohibition on retroactive laws.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="mora accipiendi" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Delay in payment or performance in the part of the creditor or obligor</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="mortis causa" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Donation that is made in contemplation of death</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="obiter dictum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>in law, an observation by a judge on some point of law not directly relevant to the case before him, and thus neither requiring his decision nor serving as a precedent, but nevertheless of persuasive authority. In general, any comment, remark or observation made in passing</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="rebus sic stantibus" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A qualification in a treaty or contract, that allows for nullification in the event fundamental circumstances change.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="de mortuis nil nisi bonum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Social convention that it is inappropriate to speak ill of the recently deceased, even if they were an enemy.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="quoad hoc" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used to mean "with respect to" some named thing, such as when stating what the law is in regards to that named thing.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in pleno" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>In full</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="se defendendo" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The act of defending one's own person or property, or the well-being or property of another.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ne exeat" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Shortened version of ne exeat repiblica: "let him not exit the republic". A writ to prevent one party to a dispute from leaving (or being taken) from the court's jurisdiction.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in personam" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used in the context of "directed at this particular person", refers to a judgement or subpoena directed at a specific named individual. C.f. in rem.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in toto" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>In total</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="a fortiori" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>An a fortiori argument is an "argument from a stronger reason", meaning that because one fact is true, that a second related and included fact must also be true.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="idem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used in citations to indicate the cited source came from the same source as the preceding one, though not necessarily the same page or location. C.f. ibid.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="de novo" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Often used in the context of "trial de novo"—a new trial ordered when the previous one failed to reach a conclusion.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="quantum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>how much</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="arguendo" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>for the sake of argument</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="lex loci" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The law of the country, state, or locality where the matter under litigation took place. Usually used in contract law, to determine which laws govern the contract.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="duces tecum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A "subpoena duces tecum" is a summons to produce physical evidence for a trial.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pro bono publico" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>/ˈproʊ ˈboʊnoʊ ˈpʌblɨkoʊ/</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="res" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>thing, matter, issue, affair</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="posse comitatus" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A body of armed citizens pressed into service by legal authority, to keep the peace or pursue a fugitive.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="nulla bona" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Notation made when a defendant has no tangible property available to be seized in order to comply with a judgement.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="negotorium gestio" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Obligation arising from good works affecting other people, obliging the creditor to pay for the reimbursement of the cost that was used in doing good works</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="mora solvendi" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Delay in payment or performance in the part of the debtor or the obligee</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ad litem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Describes a party designated to represent another party who is deemed incapable of representing him/herself (e.g. a child or incapacitated adult).</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="quid pro quo" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>An equal exchange of goods or services, or of money (or other consideration of equal value) for some goods or services.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="nihil dicit" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A judgement rendered in the absence of a plea, or in the event one party refuses to cooperate in the proceedings.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="et al." ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Abbreviation of et alii, meaning "and others".</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="veto" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The power of an executive to prevent an action, especially the enactment of legislation.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="qua" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>In the capacity of</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="scienter" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used when offenses or torts were committed with the full awareness of the one so committing.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ultra vires" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>An act that requires legal authority to perform, but which is done without obtaining that authority.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="nemo dat quod non habet" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>If someone purchases something that the seller has no right to (such as stolen property), the purchaser will likewise have no legal claim to the thing bought.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="fiat" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A warrant issued by a judge for some legal proceedings.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="corpus juris civilis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The complete collection of civil laws of a particular jurisdiction or court. Also sometimes used to refer to the Code of Justinian.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="malum in se" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Something considered a universal wrong or evil, regardless of the system of laws in effect.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="consensus facit legem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Stipulates that when two or more persons arrive at a good faith agreement, the law will insist on that agreement being carried out.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="et cetera" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Generally used in the sense of "and so forth".</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="mos pro lege" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>That which is the usual custom has the force of law.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="nota bene" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A term used to direct the reader to cautionary or qualifying statements for the main text.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="non liquet" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A type of verdict where positive guilt or innocence cannot be determined. Also called "not proven" in legal systems with such verdicts.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="videlicet" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used in documents to mean "namely" or "that is". Usually abbreviated viz.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="contra legem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used when a court or tribunal hands down a decision that is contrary to the laws of the governing state.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="forum non conveniens" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A concept wherein a court refuses to hear a particular matter, citing a more appropriate forum for the issue to be decided.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="subpoena duces tecum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>An order compelling an entity to produce physical evidence or witness in a legal matter.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jus soli" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Social law concept wherein citizenship of a nation is determined by place of birth.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pro tanto" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A partial payment of an award or claim, based on the defendant's ability to pay.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="res communis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Property constructs like airspace and water rights are said to be res communis - that is, a thing common to all, and that could not be the subject of ownership. With airspace, the difficulty has been to identify where the fee simple holder's rights to the heavens end. Water is a bit more defined — it is common until captured.[2]</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="contra" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used in case citations to indicate that the cited source directly contradicts the point being made.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="uxor" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used in documents in place of the wife's name. Usually abbreviated et ux.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="lex posterior derogat priori" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>More recent law overrules older ones on the same matter.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="qui facit per alium facit per se" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>One who delegates a task to another, takes full responsibility for the performance of that act as if he himself had done it. Basis for the law of agency</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="non adimpleti contractus" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>In the case where a contract imposes specific obligations on both parties, one side cannot sue the other for failure to meet their obligations, if the plaintiff has not themselves met their own.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="leges humanae nascuntur, vivunt, moriuntur" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Illustrates that laws are made, are in force for a period, and then become obsolete.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="uberrima fides" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Concept in contract law specifying that all parties must act with the utmost good faith.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex facie" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>If a contract is blatantly and obviously incorrect or illegal, it can be considered void ex facie without any further analysis or arguments.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pater familias" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The head of household, for purposes of considering the rights and responsibilities thereof.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="absque hoc" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>"Presenting the negative portion of a plea when pleading at common by way a special traverse."[1]</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jus tertii" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Arguments made by a third party in disputes over possession, the intent of which is to question one of the principal parties' claims of ownership or rights to ownership.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ad colligenda bona" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>to collect the goods</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex tunc" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Term used in contract law to specify terms that are voided or confirmed in effect from the execution of the contract. C.f. ex nunc.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in haec verba" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used when including text in a complaint verbatim, where its appearance in that form is germane to the case, or is required to be included.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ipsissima verba" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Referring to a document or ruling that is being quoted by another.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="r" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>King or Queen. In British cases, will see R v Freeman meaning Regina against Freeman. Changes with King or Queen on throne at time.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="adjournment sine die" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>When an assembly adjourns without setting a date for its next meeting.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ferae naturae" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Wild animals residing on unowned property do not belong to any party in a dispute on the land.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="locus delicti" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Shorthand version of Lex locus delcti commissi. The "scene of the crime".</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="de die in diem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Generally refers to a type of labor in which the worker is paid fully at the completion of each day's work.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="vinculum juris" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Something which is legally binding.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="felo de se" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A suicide. This archaic term stems from English common law, where suicide was legally a felony, thus a person who committed suicide was treated as a felon for purposes of estate disposal.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex post" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Based on knowledge of the past.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="sui juris" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to one legally competent to manage his own affairs. Also spelled sui iuris.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="a mensa et thoro" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Divorce a mensa et thoro indicates legal separation without legal divorce.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pro bono" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Professional work done for free.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="locus standi" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The right of a party to appear and be heard before a court.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="corpus delicti" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A person cannot be convicted of a crime, unless it can be proven that the crime was even committed.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="periculum in mora" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A condition given to support requests for urgent action, such as a protective order or restraining order.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ei incumbit probatio qui dicit" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The concept that one is innocent until proven guilty.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="per curiam" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A decision delivered by a multi-judge panel, such as an appellate court, in which the decision is said to be authored by the court itself, instead of situations where those individual judges supporting the decision are named.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="dramatis personae" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Persons of the drama</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="de integro" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Often used to mean "start it all over", in the context of "repeat de integro".</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="favor contractus" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A concept in treaty law that prefers the maintaining of a contract over letting it expire for purely procedural reasons.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ad hominem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Attacking an opponent's character rather than answering his argument.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="compos mentis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Of sound mind. Also used in the negative "Non compos mentis", meaning "Not of sound mind".</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="nemo plus iuris ad alium transferre potest quam ipse habet" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A purchaser of stolen goods will not become the rightful owner thereof, since the seller himself was not the owner to begin with.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ad quod damnum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used in tort law. Implies that the reward or penalty ought to correspond to the damage suffered or inflicted.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex delicto" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The consequence of a crime or tort.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pro forma" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Things done as formalities.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="expressio unius est exclusio alterius" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>When items are listed, anything not explicitly stated is assumed to not be included.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in mitius" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A type of retroactive law that decriminalizes offenses committed in the past. Also known as an amnesty law.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex ante" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Essentially meaning "before the event", usually used when forecasting future events.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="quareitur" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The question is raised. Used to declare that a question is being asked in the following verbiage.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="compensatio morae" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Delay in payment or performance on the part of both the debtor and the creditor</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="mala fide" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A condition of being fraudulent or deceptive in act or belief.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="per minas" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used as a defense, when illegal acts were performed under duress</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="subpoena ad testificandum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>An order compelling an entity to give oral testimony in a legal matter.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="quo warranto" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A request made to someone exercising some power, to show by what legal right they are exercising that power. A type of writ.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="uno flatu" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used to criticize inconsistencies in speech or testimony, as in: one says one thing, and in the same breath, says another contradictory thing.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="coram non judice" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to a legal proceeding without a judge, or with a judge who does not have proper jurisdiction.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pacta sunt servanda" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A fundamental principle of law</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="res publica christiana" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>All things of concern to the worldwide body of Christianity</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="per incuriam" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A judgement given without reference to precedent.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="quo ante" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Returning to a specific state of affairs which preceded some defined action.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="rex non potest peccare" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used to describe the basis for sovereign immunity</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="nisi" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A decree that does not enter into force unless some other specified condition is met.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="nemo auditur propriam turpitudinem allegans" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Nobody can bring a case that stems from their own illegal act</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ultra posse nemo obligatur" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Specifies that one should do what he can to support the community, but since everyone has different levels of ability, it cannot be expected that all will perform the same.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in camera" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Conducted in private, or in secret. The opposite of in open court.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="seriatim" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Describes the process in which the court hears assorted matters in a specific order. Also refers to an occasion where a multiple-judge panel will issue individual opinions from the members, rather than a single ruling from the entire panel.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="solutio indebiti" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Obligation arising from undue payment, obliging the debtor to return the undue payment.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="liberum veto" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>An aspect of a unanimous voting system, whereby any member can end discussion on a proposed law.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex post facto" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Commonly said as "after the fact."</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="de minimis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Various legal areas concerning small amounts or small degrees.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ejusdem generis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Known as a "canon of construction", it states that when a limited list of specific things also includes a more general class, that the scope of that more general class shall be limited to other items more like the specific items in the list.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="et vir" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Usually used instead of naming a woman's husband as a party in a case.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex fida bona" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Good business norms</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="res nullius" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Ownerless property or goods. Such property or goods are able and subject to being owned by anybody.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="contradictio in adjecto" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A contradiction in terms.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in terrorem clause" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A clause in a will that threatens any party who contests the will with being disinherited. Also called a no-contest clause.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="amicus curiae" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A person who offers information to a court regarding a case before it.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="a posteriori" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>An argument derived from subsequent event</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="imprimatur" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>An authorization for a document to be printed. Used in the context of approval by a religious body or other censoring authority.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ad hoc" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Generally signifies a solution designed for a specific problem or task, non-generalizable, and not intended to be able to be adapted to other purposes.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="lingua franca" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A language common to an area that is spoken by all, even if not their mother tongue. Term derives from the name given to a common language used by traders in the Mediterranean basin dating from the Middle Ages.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="respondeat superior" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A concept that the master (e.g. employer) is responsible for the actions of his subordinates (e.g. employees).</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="mandamus" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A writ issue by a higher court to a lower one, ordering that court or related officials to perform some administrative duty. Often used in the context of legal oversight of government agencies.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="lex retro non agit" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A law cannot make something illegal that was legal at the time it was performed. See ex post facto law.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="a quo" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Regarding a court of first instance, or the decision/s of a previous court, known as the courta quo.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="lacunae" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A situation arising that is not covered by any law. Generally used in International Law, as all countries codify according to their own systems of law.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ipse dixit" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>An assertion given undue weight solely by virtue of the person making the assertion.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in limine" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A motion to a judge in a case that is heard and considered outside the presence of the jury.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="sub nomine" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Abbreviated sub nom.; used in case citations to indicate that the official name of a case changed during the proceedings, usually after appeal (e.g., rev'd sub nom. and aff'd sub nom.)</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in rem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used in the context of a case against property, as opposed to a particular person. See also in rem jurisdiction. C.f. in personam.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="inter arma enim silent leges" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A concept that during war, many illegal activities occur. Also taken to mean that in times of war, laws are suppressed, ostensibly for the good of the country.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ante" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>before</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="actori incumbit probatio" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The burden of proof, Roman law</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="i.e." ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Abbreviation of id est, meaning "that is", in the sense of restating something that may not have been clear.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="par delictum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used when both parties to a dispute are at fault</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="stare decisis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The obligation of a judge to stand by a prior precedent.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in extenso" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>In extended form, or at full length. Often used to refer to publication of documents, where it means the full unabridged document is published.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pro per" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Representing oneself, without counsel. Also known as pro se representation.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="locus poenitentiae" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>When one party withdraws from a contract before all parties are bound.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in solidum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Where a group of persons share liability for a debt, such as co-signers to a loan, the debtor can sue a single party in solidum, that is, to recover the entire amount owed.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="salus populi suprema lex esto" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used variously as a motto, a reminder, or a notion of how the law and governments in general should be.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="corpus juris secundum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>An encyclopedia of US law drawn from US Federal and State court decisions.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="extant" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to things that are currently existing at a given point, rather than things that are no longer so.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="propria persona" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to one reperesenting themselves without the services of a lawyer. Also known as pro per representation.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="sub judice" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to a matter currently being considered by the court.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="per stirpes" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>An estate of a decedent is distributed per stirpes, if each branch of the family is to receive an equal share of an estate.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="cadit quaestio" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Indicates that a settlement to a dispute or issue has been reached, and the issue is now resolved.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex rel" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Abbreviation of ex relatione. Used when the government brings a case that arises from the information conveyed to it by a third party ("relator").</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="dictum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A statement given some weight or consideration due to the respect given the person making it.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ne bis in idem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Prohibition against double jeopardy. A legal action cannot be brought twice for the same act or offense.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in forma pauperis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Someone unable to afford the costs associated with a legal proceeding. As this will not be a barrier to seeking justice, such persons are given in forma pauperis status (usually abbreviated IFP), wherein most costs are waived or substantially reduced.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="sine die" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used when the court is adjourning without specifying a date to re-convene. See also adjournment sine die.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="uti possidetis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Ancient concept regarding conflicts, wherein all property possessed by the parties at the conclusion of the conflict shall remain owned by those parties unless treaties to the contrary are enacted.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="per quod" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used in legal documents in the same sense as "whereby". A per quod statement is typically used to show that specific acts had consequences which form the basis for the legal action.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="status quo" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>In contract law, in a case of innocent representation, the injured party is entitled to be replaced in statu quo. Note the common usage is status quo from the Latin status quo ante, the "state in which before" or "the state of affairs that existed previously."</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="bona fide" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Implies sincere good intention regardless of outcome.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="mens rea" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>One of the requirements for a crime to be committed, the other being actus reus, the guilt act. This essentially is the basis for the notion that those without sufficient mental capability cannot be judged guilty of a crime.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="supra" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used in citations to refer to a previously cited source.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="functus officio" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A person, court, statute, or legal document that has no legal authority, because its original legal purpose has been fulfilled.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="status quo ante" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>In contract law, in a case of innocent representation, the injured party is entitled to be replaced in statu quo. Note the common usage is status quo from the Latin status quo ante, the "state in which before" or "the state of affairs that existed previously."</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="suggestio falsi" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A false statement made in the negotiation of a contract.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex injuria jus non oritur" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A principle in international law that unjust acts cannot create laws.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="praetor peregrinus" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The Roman Praetor (magistrate) responsible for matters involving non-Romans.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in pari materia" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to a situation where a law or statute may be ambiguous, and similar laws applying to the matter are used to interpret the vague one.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="de minimis non curat lex" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>There must be a minimal level of substance or impact in order to bring a legal action.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="contra bonos mores" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Contracts so made are generally illegal and unenforceable.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="post mortem auctoris" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used in reference to intellectual property rights, which usually are based around the author's lifetime.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jus inter gentes" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Laws governing treaties and international agreements.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ceteris paribus" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>More commonly rendered in English as "All other things being equal."</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="guardian ad litem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>An independent party appointed in family law disputes to represent parties that cannot represent themselves, such as minors, developmentally disabled, or elderly.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="subpoena" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A writ compelling testimony, the production of evidence, or some other action, under penalty for failure to do so.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="malum prohibitum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Something wrong or illegal by virtue of it being expressly prohibited, that might not otherwise be so.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in prope persona" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>One who represents themselves in court without the [official] assistance of an attorney.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="prius quam exaudias ne iudices" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>before you hear, do not judge</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="maleficia propositis distinguuntur" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>evil acts are distinguished from evil purposes[4] crimes are distinguished by the intention[5]</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ad coelum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Abbreviated from Cuius est solum eius est usque ad coelum et ad infernos which translates to "[for] whoever owns [the] soil, [it] is his all the way [up] to Heaven and [down] to Hell." The principle that the owner of a parcel of land also owns the air above and the ground below the parcel.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jus in bello" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Laws governing the conduct of parties in war.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in omnibus" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used to mean "in every respect." Something applying to every aspect of a situation.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="juris et de jure" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Incontrovertible and fundamental presumptions of law. One cannot argue against, or try to otherwise refute these.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ab extra" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Concerning a case, a person may have received some funding from a 3rd party. This funding may have been considered ab extra.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="habeas corpus" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A writ used to challenge the legality of detention. Orders the detaining party to "have the (living) body" of the detained brought before the court where the detention will be investigated.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="vide" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used in citations to refer the reader to another location.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="stratum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>1) In property law, condominiums has said to occupy stratum many stories about the ground. 2) Stratum can also be a societial level made up of individuals with similar status of social, cultural or economic nature. 3) Stratum can refer to classification in an organized system along the lines of layers, levels, divisions, or similar grouping.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ratio decidendi" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The point in a legal proceeding, or the legal precedent so involved, which led to the final decision being what it was.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="nunc pro tunc" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>An action by a court to correct a previous procedural or clerical error.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="parens patriae" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to the power of the State to act as parent to a child when the legal parents are unable or unwilling.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="crimen falsi" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Forgery.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="suppressio veri" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Willful concealment of the truth when bound to reveal it, such as withholding details of damage from an auto accident from a prospective buyer of the car in that accident.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in absentia" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A legal proceeding conducted without the presence of one party is said to be conducted in absentia, e.g., trial in absentia or being sentenced in absentia.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="trinoda necessitas" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to a threefold tax levied on Anglo-Saxon citizens to cover roads, buildings, and the military.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="animus revertendi" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>"Wild animals, such as bees and homing pigeons, that by habit go 'home' to their possessor. Used when discussing ferae naturae."[2]</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="casus fortuitus" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>When H.M.S. Bounty was destroyed by Hurricane Sandy, October 29, 2012, Casus Fortuitus would describe the H.M.S. Bounty being at the wrong place when Hurricane Sandy came up the coast.HMS Bounty Sinks</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ignorantia juris non excusat" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A principle that states that not having knowledge of a law is not an excuse for breaking it.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="debellatio" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Complete annihilation of a warring party, bringing about the end of the conflict.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in esse" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Actually existing in reality. Opposite of in posse.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="sua sponte" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Some action taken by the court or another official body, without the prompting of another party.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in futuro" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to things to come, or things that may occur later but are not so now.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="modus operandi" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A person's particular way of doing things. Used when using behavioral analysis while investigating a crime. Often abbreviated "M.O."</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="contra proferentem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used in contract law to stipulate that an ambiguous term in a contract shall be interpreted against the interests of the party that insisted upon the term's inclusion. Prevents the intentional additions of ambiguous terminology from being exploited by the party who insisted on its inclusion.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="fiat justitia ruat caelum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Also sometimes a motto, a legal maxim that justice must be done regardless of the result otherwise.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="prior tempore potior iure" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A legal principle that older laws take precedent over newer ones. Another name for this principle is lex posterior.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="res judicata" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A matter that has been finally adjudicated, meaning no further appeals or legal actions by the involved parties is now possible.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="non est inventus" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Reported by a sheriff on writ when the defendant cannot be found in his county or jurisdiction.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="de facto" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Literally "from fact"; often used to mean something that is true in practice, but has not been officially instituted or endorsed. "For all intents and purposes". Cf. de jure.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jus civile" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A codified set of laws concerning citizenry, and how the laws apply to them.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="dolus specialis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Heavily used in the context of genocide in international law.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="consensus ad idem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Parties must be of one mind and their promises must relate to the subject or object[3]</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="inter rusticos" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to contract, debts, or other agreements made between parties who are not legal professionals.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jus ad bellum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to legalities considered before entering into a war, to ensure it is legal to go to war initially. Not to be confused with ius in bello (q.v.), the "laws of war" concerning how war is carried out.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="post mortem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to an autopsy, or as a qualification as to when some event occurred.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="infra" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Below or Under</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex officio" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Something done or realized by the fact of holding an office or position.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="vis major" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Events over which no humans have control, and so cannot be held responsible. An "Act of God". In law, the more common term is the French phrase 'Force majeure'. See also casus fortuitus (chance occurrence).</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="vigilantibus non dormientibus aequitas subvenit" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Concept that if an opposing party unreasonably delays bringing an action, that it is no longer considered just to hear their claim, due to fundamental changes in circumstance brought upon by their delay.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="lis alibi pendens" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to requesting a legal dispute be heard that is also being heard by another court. To avoid possibly contradictory judgements, this request will not be granted.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="intra fauces terra" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>This term refers to a nation's territorial waters.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pro tempore" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Something, such as an office held, that is temporary.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="innuendo" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>An intimation about someone or something, made indirectly or vaguely suggesting the thing being implied. Often used when the implied thing is negative or derogatory.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ad valorem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>according to value</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ibid." ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Abbreviation of ibidem, meaning "in the same place. Used when citing sources, to indicate the cited source came from the identical location as the preceding one.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="locus" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Place</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in extremis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>In extreme circumstances. Often used to refer to "at the point of death."</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="nulla poena sine lege" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>One cannot be prosecuted for doing something that is not prohibited by law.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="a priori" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>An argument derived from previous event</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="res ipsa loquitur" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>used in tort law when there is no proof of what caused the harm, but it is most likely only the thing that could have caused the harm</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="delegatus non potest delegare" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>That which has been delegated, cannot delegate [further]</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="condicio sine qua non" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>An indispensable and essential action, condition, or ingredient.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="per contra" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Legal shorthand for "in contrast to"</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in terrorem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A warning or threat to sue, made in the hopes of convincing the other party to take action to avoid a lawsuit.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="intra vires" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Something done which requires legal authority, and the act is performed accordingly. C.f.ultra vires.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="dubia in meliorem partem interpretari debent" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Often spoken as "to give the benefit of the doubt."</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jus gentium" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Customary law followed by all nations. Nations being at peace with one another, without having to have an actual peace treaty in force, would be an example of this concept.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="de futuro" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>At a future date.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jus accrescendri" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>In property law, on the death of one tenant, that tenant's interest passes automatically to the surviving tenant(s) to hold jointly until the estate is held by a sole tenant. The only way to defeat the right of survivorship is to sever the joint tenancy during the lifetime of the parties, jus accrescendi takes priority over a will or interstate accession rules.[2]</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jus" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Essentially: Law.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex turpi causa non oritur actio" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A party cannot bring a legal action for consequences of his own illegal act.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="bona vacantia" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>ownerless goods</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="eo nomine" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>By that name.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ipso facto" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used in the context that one event is a direct and immediate consequence of another. "In and of itself."</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="res gestae" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Differing meaning depending on what type of law is involved. May refer to the complete act of a felony, from start to finish, or may refer to statements given that may be exempt from hearsay rules.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="mare liberum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A body of water open to all. Typically a synonym for International Waters, or in other legal parlance, the "High Seas".</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in situ" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Often used in the context of decisions or rulings about a property or thing "left in place" after the case as it was before.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="gravamen" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The basic element or complaint of a lawsuit.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="factum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>1. an assured statement made; 2. completion of a will and all its parts to make it valid and legal; 3). book of facts and law presented in a Canadian court</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="fieri facias" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A writ ordering the local law enforcement to ensure that damages awarded by the court are properly recovered. A writ of execution.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="jus cogens" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Internationally agreed laws that bear no deviation, and do not require treaties to be in effect. An example is law prohibiting genocide.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="caveat emptor" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>In addition to the general warning, also refers to a legal doctrine wherein a buyer could not get relief from a seller for defects present on property which rendered it unfit for use.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="alter ego" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A second identity living within a person.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="generalia specialibus non derogant" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Specifies that a certain matter of law be covered by the most specific laws pertaining, in the event that broader laws conflict with the specific one.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="intra" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Within</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="donatio mortis causa" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>"The donor, contemplating imminent death, declares words of present gifting and delivers the gift to the donee or someone who clearly takes possession on behalf of the donee. The gift becomes effective at death but remains revocable until that time."[2]</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="qui tam" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>In a qui tam action, one who assists the prosecution of a case is entitled to a proportion of any fines or penalties assessed.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="scandalum magnatum" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Defamation against a peer in British law. Now repealed as a specific offense.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="vel non" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used when considering whether some event or situation is either present or it is not.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="nolo contendere" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A type of plea whereby the defendant neither admits nor denies the charge. Commonly interpreted as "No contest."</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ex nunc" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Term used in contract law to specify terms that are voided or confirmed in effect only in the future and not prior to the contract, or its adjudication. C.f. ex tunc.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="casus belli" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The justification for acts of war.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="ad idem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>In agreement.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="inter se" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to obligations between members of the same group or party, differentiated from the whole party's obligations to another party.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="in flagrante delicto" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Caught in the actual act of committing a crime. Often used as a euphemism for a couple caught in the act of sexual intercourse, though it technically refers to being "caught in the act" of any misdeed.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="reddendo singula singulis" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>The canon of construction that in a list of items containing a qualifying phrase at the end, the qualifier refers only to the last item in the list.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="affidavit" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>A formal statement of fact.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="quantum meruit" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>In contract law, a quasi-contractual remedy that permits partial reasonable payment for an incomplete piece of work (services and/or materials), assessed proportionately, where no price is established when the request is made. In contract law, and in particular the requirement for consideration, if no fixed price is agreed upon for the service and/or materials, then one party would request a reasonable price for the said services and/or materials at the end of the job. A common example would be a plumber requested to fix a leak in the middle of the night.[3]</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="inter alia" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Used to indicate an item cited has been pulled from a larger or more complete list.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="de jure" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Literally "from law"; something that is established in law, whether or not it is true in general practice. Cf. de facto.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="pro tem" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Something, such as an office held, that is temporary.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
<juridicaljargon jj="erga omnes" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_legal_Latin_terms">
<description>Refers to rights or obligations that are owed towards all.</description>

</juridicaljargon>
</juridaljargonSet>